Guide to the Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990 AIS.1977.33
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Individual Case Files, 1946-1975; V.
  - Political Cases, 1.
    - Steve Nelson, 1949-1959
      - United States v. Mesarosh, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
        These files contain newspaper clippings and preliminary census records from 1950 used as exhibits in the United States v. Mesarosh case.
      - Jury Selection, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        This file includes correspondence to U.S. Jury Commissioner in the Western District of Pennsylvania William L. Potts which lists the names of several people he deems fit to be added to a Federal jury wheel. Potts sent letters to various companies in the Pittsburgh area requesting the names of qualified employees. A sample of such a letter is present in the file. The defendants later argued that this procedure demonstrated biases in the jury selection process.
      - United States v. Steve Nelson (Box 7, Folder 5)
        This file includes an affidavit of Steve Nelson regarding his sedition trial and issues of Political Affairs. Also included is the army discharge certificate of Irving Weissman, a co-defendant.
      - United States v. Steve Nelson (Box 7, Folder 6)
        This file includes publications on Marxist philosophy and World War II, as well as newspaper clippings from The Worker and a Communist party membership application.
      - Correspondence with Margaret Nelson, 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        This file contains correspondence regarding Mrs. Nelson's injuries due to a car accident.
  - Miscellaneous Cases, 2.
    These files contain correspondence and legal papers relating to a variety of court cases. Examples of estate, personal injury, and child support cases are present. Inmate appeals while in jail challenging court procedure are also included in these documents.
    - Apanowicz, Stanley Personal Injury Case, 1954-1964 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Bishop, Margaret Personal Injury Case, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Black, Virginia A. Personal Injury Case, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Cannon, James Jailhouse Appeal, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
    - Clymire, Walter Personal Injury Case, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Csuk, Ferenc Estate, 1959-1962 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Dupeshka Estate, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Fleming, James Jailhouse Appeal, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Gasparovich, Frank Personal Injury Case, 1954-1958 (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
    - Gilchrist, James M. Personal Injury Case, 1960s (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
    - Harris, Frank Personal Injury Case, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Hatalski Estate, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Haywood, Robert E. Jailhouse Appeal, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Janosko, Michael Personal injury Case, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Karamarkovich, John Personal Injury Case, 1950-1970 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Langloss, Eva R. Personal Injury Case, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Levine, Richard Steven Referred Case, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Logan, James Referred Case, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - McKee, Robert C. Jailhouse Appeal, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Magath, John Estate, 1954-1972 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Pewatts, John Child Support Case, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Pierka, Frank Estate, 1957-1971 (Box 7, Folder 32-33)
    - Reynolds, Charles W. Personal Injury Case, 1945-1955 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Richardson, James B. Personal Injury Case, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Richardson, John C. Personal Injury Case, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Sedlock, Paul Personal Injury Case, 1963-1972 (Box 7, Folder 37-38)
    - Shapele, Blade Estate, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Wounick v. Hillman Transportation Co. Personal Injury Case, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 40-41)
    - Zubritsky, John Estate, 1957-1967 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Cases by Category, 1947-1973; VI.
  This series contains information on the various types of cases Schlesinger participated in. Many of the denaturalization files contain legal papers regarding the cases of Steve Nelson/Mesarosh and Julia Misloy. Denaturalization and deportation files include a variety of papers, correspondence, and pamphlets regarding the Committee to Protect Foreign Born and people who were involved in denaturalization cases. Files regarding estate, jail, prison, and workhouse cases contain correspondence regarding specific cases.
  - Denaturalization, 1954-1958 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Denaturalization, 1954-1956 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Nelson/Mesarosh Denaturalization, 1954-1957 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Misloy Denaturalization, 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Denaturalization and Deportation, 1954-1957 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Deportation, 1954-1957 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Deportation and Denaturalization Materials (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - Estate Files, 1947-1949, 1964-1970 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Jail Cases, 1951-1961 (Box 9, Folder 12-14)
  - Prison Workhouse, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Prison Case (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Writ of Prohibition, State Supreme Court, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Legal and Political Documents, 1942-1975; VII.
  This series contains correspondence and legal papers regarding a variety of Schlesinger's court cases. In addition to files relating to specific cases and jailhouse correspondence, there is information regarding Schlesinger's involvement in lobbying for a State Bureau of Child Nurseries in the 1940s and on anti-Semitism.
  - Communist Party's Line on "The Negro Question", 1940s (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1975 (Box 9, Folder 19-26)
  - War Nurseries and Daycares, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 28-29)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Raid on the Jewish Cultural Center, 1950-1955 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Political Letters, 1951, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Court Papers and Clippings, 1951-1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Cleveland Correspondence, 1954-1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Cases, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Leon David Kogan regarding Cvetic Testimony, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Bill to Aid Paupers in Litigation (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Crank Letters (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - File Cover (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Personal Correspondence and Financial Papers, 1927-1975; VIII.
  This series contains Schlesinger's personal documents. Included are financial papers, leases, and photographs of Schlesinger. Also present is correspondence regarding his family business in Scranton, Pa., family, medical conditions, and insurance
  - Personal Correspondence, 1950-1975 (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1955-1963 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Tom Fitzpatrick, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Personal Letters, 1950s (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Personal Information, 1940s (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Financial Papers, 1950s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 17-22)
  - Application for Service in the Armed Forces, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Schlesinger, ca.1941 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence with Art Shields regarding an Article, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Medical Problems, 1958-1964 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Fire at Butler County Residence, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Leases, 1946-1950, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Eyeglass Prescription (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Motor Vehicle Registration Transfer, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Insurance and Subscriptions (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Schlesinger Family Correspondence, 1953-1965 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Kaufman, Schlesinger and Nogi, 1927-1928 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Adolf Schlesinger, Father, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Anna Schlesinger, Mother, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Harry Dragan and Mother Bloor-Omholt, 1946-1951 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Jacob (Jack) Schlesinger, Brother, 1952-1954 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Sylvia Schlesinger (m. Strauss), Sister, 1951-1959 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Dorothy Schlesinger (m. Solomon), Sister, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Ida Schlesinger, Wife, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Mirowitz, Wife's Family (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Miriam Schlesinger, Daughter, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Daniel Schlesinger, Son, 1953-1958 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Momo Taro Parable (Box 10, Folder 44)
- Organizations, 1946-1976; IX.
  These files contain information relating to various organizations throughout the country. These organizations were concerned with civil rights, Communism, legal issues, and labor rights. Included are clippings and literature concerning the efforts of the groups.
  - All Nations Harvest Festival, Pittsburgh, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, New York, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, New York, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Citizens' Committee to End the Stool Pigeon Racket, Pittsburgh, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Civil Rights Congress, New York, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Civil Rights Congress, Pittsburgh, 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Committee to Defend Jewish Culture, Pittsburgh, 1955-1957 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Committee to Elect a Negro Congressman, Pittsburgh, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Committee to End Sedition Laws, Pittsburgh, 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Communist Party of Illinois, Chicago (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Communist Party of Western Pennsylvania, 1946, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Communist Party U.S.A., 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, New York, 1954-1961 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Freedom of the Press Committee, Pittsburgh, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Independent Voters League, Pittsburgh, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine and Furniture Workers (IUE), 1955 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Denver, 1955, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - International Workers Order (IWO), 1957 (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - International Workers Order Cemetery, Wildwood, Pennsylvania, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Jewish Arts Committee, Pittsburgh, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Miscellaneous Defense Organizations, 1950-1961 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - National Alliance Against Racial and Political Repression, Western Pennsylvania Chapter, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee, Los Angeles, 1960, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - National Assembly for Democratic Rights, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National Lawyers Guild, 1947-1976 (Box 11, Folder 2-7)
  - Nationality Committee of Western Pennsylvania, Pittsburgh, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Ohio Bill of Rights Conference, Cleveland, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Ohio Civil Rights Congress, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Ohio Valley Fraternal Club, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh Committee to Secure Justice for Morton Sobell, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Pittsburgh Forum, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh Friends of the Council of Federated Organizations, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh National Bank, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Serbian Progressive Club, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Steel City Industrial Union Council, Pittsburgh, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), New York, 1952-1954 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - W.E.B. DuBois Clubs of America, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Western Pennsylvania Constitutional Liberties Information Center, 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1961; X.
  This series contains newspaper clippings regarding Schlesinger's legal work, Communism in the Pittsburgh region, and the hearings of Matthew Cvetic and other informers before the House Un-American Activities Committee.
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1953-1961 (Box 11, Folder 22-32)
  - Clippings regarding Communism, 1953-1959 (Box 11, Folder 33-34)
  - Clippings regarding Informers, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Mounted Newspaper Clippings (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Photocopies of Newspaper Clippings (Box 11, Folder 37)
- Card File Bibliography, XI.
  The card file bibliography was compiled by Schlesinger as a way of cataloging newspaper articles in which he, his cases, and other persons, organizations, and events of interest were mentioned. Examples include Matthew Cvetic, Joseph Mazzei, Steve Nelson, Michael J. Musmanno, and Benjamin Davis.
  - Card File Bibliography (Box 12-13)
- Publications, 1927-1976; XII.
  These publications generally relate to legal issues arising in connection with Schlesinger's work on behalf of alleged Communists. Other manuals are concerned with labor rights and immigration within the United States. Legal documents from specific cases are also present.
  - NACCA Law Journal, May 1948 (Box 14, Volume 1)
  - Lawyers Guild Review, 1959-1960 (Box 14, Volume 2-5)
  - The Guild Lawyer, May 1959-July 1962 (Box 14, Volume 6-25)
  - Pittsburgh Legal Journal, May 14, 1960 (Box 14, Volume 26)
  - Case and Comment, 1961, 1973-1976 (Box 14, Volume 27-32)
  - Review of Contemporary Law, June, 1962 (Box 14, Volume 33)
  - Pittsburgh Legal Journal, January, 1975 (Box 14, Volume 34)
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association Quarterly, January, 1975 (Box 14, Volume 35)
  - Trial, May 1975-April 1976 (Box 14, Volume 36-43)
  - University of Pittsburgh Law Review, Summer 1976 (Box 14, Volume 44)
  - The Building Trades Handbook, 1927 (Box 14, Volume 45)
  - Normalization of World Trade and the Monetary Problem by A. Smirnov, 1952 (Box 14, Volume 46)
  - Safety Guide for Unions by the National Safety Council, 1962 (Box 14, Volume 47)
  - Safety Standards, March-April, 1971 (Box 14, Volume 48)
  - Labor Newsletter, October 1974 (Box 14, Volume 49)
  - Socialism: What's In It For You by A.B. Magil, 1946 (Box 14, Volume 50)
  - In Defense of the Communist Party and the Indicted Leaders by William Z. Foster, 1949 (Box 14, Volume 51)
  - The Walter-McCarran Law by The Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, 1952 (Box 14, Volume 52)
  - In the Shadow of Liberty by Abner Green, 1954 (Box 14, Volume 53)
  - The Constitutional Status of the Lawfully Admitted Permanent Resident Alien by Siegfried Hesse, 1959 (Box 14, Volume 54)
  - World Marxist Review, February 1961 (Box 14, Volume 55)
  - The Ideological Struggle in the American Left, 1963 (Box 14, Volume 56)
  - Goldwaterism by Mike Newberry, 1964 (Box 14, Volume 57)
  - Political Affairs, 1964, 1969-1970 (Box 14, Volume 58-60)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights Docket Report, 1975 (Box 14, Volume 61)
  - 30th Anniversary of the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (Box 14, Volume 62)
  - Is Communism Un-American? by Eugene Dennis (Box 14, Volume 63)
  - Legal Documents
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries contains court documents from cases relating to various suits Schlesinger was working on. Also included is a report from the Committee on Un-American Activities regarding Communism.
    - Superior Court of Pennsylvania, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania v. Philip Scasserra, Brief for Appellee, 1962 (Box 14, Volume 64)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Third Circuit, Brief for Mosites Construction Company and S.T. Mosites, Appellees (Box 14, Volume 65)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Third Circuit, Brief for Appellee and Appendix for Mosites Case (Box 14, Volume 66)
    - United States Court of Appeals, District of Columbia Circuit, Brief for Appellant, The Communist Party of the United States of America v. United States of America (Box 14, Volume 67)
    - United States Court of Appeals, District of Columbia Circuit, Brief for WSP as Amicus Curiae (Box 14, Volume 68)
    - United States Court of Appeals, District of Columbia Circuit, Brief for Appellant, Arthur Kinoy v. District of Columbia (Box 14, Volume 69)
    - Supreme Court of the United States, Brief for Petitioners, William Albertson and Roscoe Quincy Proctor v. Subversive Activities Control Board, 1965 (Box 14, Volume 70)
    - Supreme Court of the United States, Jurisdictional Statement, Jeremiah Stamler, M.D. and Yolanda F. Hall and Milton M. Cohen v. Hon. Edwin E. Willis, et al., 1968 (Box 14, Volume 71)
    - Supreme Court of the United States, Appendicies 4 and 5 to Jurisdictional Statement, Jeremiah Stamler, M.D. and Yolanda F. Hall and Milton M. Cohen v. Hon. Edwin E. Willis, et al., 1968 (Box 14, Volume 72)
    - House of Representatives, United States Congress, Brief of Contestants Urging the Vacating of the Contested Seats and the Holding of New Elections (Box 14, Volume 73)
    - Communist Political Subversion Committee on Un-American Activities, 1957 (Box 14, Volume 74)
- Additional Cases, XIII.
  Access Restrictions
  Access to these files have been restricted. For access please contact the Archives Service Center.
  - Gerchman, Carl G. [RESTRICTED], 1960s (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Kessler, John [RESTRICTED] (Box 15, Folder 3)